Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Eero Saarinen collection
1880-2004
1938-1962
MS 593
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1379
(767 boxes)
The Eero Saarinen collection includes drawings, photographs, correspondence, writings, clippings, and audio-visual material relating to Saarinen's professional work as an architect, as well as a small amount of personal material created by himself and his wife, Aline Saarinen. A small amount of material in this collection documents the work of his father, architect Eliel Saarinen.
Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961
Conditions Governing Access
While this collection as a whole is available for research, parts of it may be restricted due to law, university policy or fragility. Any restricted material will be noted as such.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Aline Saarinen, 1971; Robert Scobey and the firm of Cooper, Dunham, Clark, Griffin & Moran, 1982; Peter C. Papademetriou, 1987; Brackley Shaw, 1988; Charles Dibbell, 1992; Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates, 2003-2005, 2008-2010; Robert A. M. Stern, 2004; Gerald D. Hines School of Architecture, University of Houston, 2004; Oliver Lundquist, 2004; Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan, 2006; Will Miller and Irwin Management Company, 2010-2011; Jayne Merkel, 2011; Pelli Clarke Pelli Architects, 2011; D. Thomas Kincaid, 2011; Frederick T. Kubitz, 2014.
Related Material
Aline and Eero Saarinen Papers, Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution.
Saarinen Collection, Yale Art Gallery.
Saarinen Family Papers, Cranbrook Archives, Cranbrook Educational Community.
Richard Gamble Knight Papers, MS 1999, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and eight additions: I. Personal Papers, 1920-2004 (inclusive), 1940-1961 (bulk). II. Professional Papers, 1909-1990. III. Office Records, 1880-1985. IV. Project Records, 1936-1989 (inclusive), 1941-1962 (bulk). V. Audio-Visual Materials, 1956-1961, undated.
Scope and Contents
The Eero Saarinen Collection is a rich source of documentation about this noted American architect, whose short, prolific career coincided with one of the most economically and culturally expansive decades in American history. Beginning with Saarinen's earliest work at the firm of his father, Eliel Saarinen, and ending with documentation of projects completed after his death, this collection contains information about all of Saarinen's projects, major and minor, built and unbuilt.
The collection consists primarily of drawings and photographs from each of the projects, with scattered amounts of correspondence, product samples, publicity materials, specifications, clippings from period publications, reference materials, and audio-visual materials pertaining to the projects. The collection also contains material pertaining to Saarinen's childhood and personal life, his professional activities, and the administrative and publicity records of his firm, Eero Saarinen and Associates. A small amount of material on the life and work of Eliel Saarinen is also available in this collection.
Little correspondence between Saarinen and his clients or contractors exists in this collection; it was apparently destroyed before the collection was donated to Yale. The two projects in the collection that do have significant amounts of correspondence associated with them are the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial in St. Louis, Missouri and the North Christian Church in Columbus, Indiana. Not all projects in the collection are documented at the same level: for example, the David S. Ingalls Rink at Yale University is documented by only three original drawings, whereas the Trans World Air Lines Terminal [Trans World Flight Center] at John F. Kennedy Airport fills more than 13 tubes of drawings.
Material from all accessions in the Saarinen collection has been merged into one single manuscript group. These materials came into Yale's custody in two main accessions. The first donation came from Aline Saarinen, Eero Saarinen's widow, in 1971. It was deposited in the Art and Architecture Library at Yale, and manuscript material was transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in 1976. This donation consisted primarily of personal materials, childhood and family photographs, audio-visual materials, materials pertaining to Eliel Saarinen, some of Aline Saarinen's personal papers, and early design sketches of various buildings. Additional materials, including watercolor sketches and travel sketchbooks, were transferred to the Yale Art Gallery by the Library in 1976. In 2002, Kevin Roche, the principal of Saarinen's successor firm Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates, donated all of the job files, publicity materials, drawings, and photographs that had been in the possession of the firm since Saarinen's death in 1961. Processing of these materials began in 2002 and was finished in 2006. Additional materials were donated to the collection by Oliver Lundquist, a former associate of Saarinen's, and by the Bentley Historical Library in Ann Arbor, Michigan. Travel slides belonging to Saarinen that had originally been housed in the Visual Resources Collection at Yale were transferred to Manuscripts and Archives in 2005.
The current arrangement of the collection reflects a re-working of the order in which the materials were received to incorporate the various accessions into one comprehensive scheme. Due to the varying size of the materials in the collection and the need to provide a logical intellectual order within series, box numbers in this collection are non-sequential. Cross-references to oversize boxes are provided when items were divided, or when related material may be found in another box. Further arrangement decisions are noted in the series-level description within the finding aid.
The Eero Saarinen collection saw a great deal of research use prior to its being formally processed at Yale. An in-house researcher at the successor firm arranged the papers, interfiling notes and photocopies of other repositories' holdings. These were removed during processing.
This collection is arranged in five series: Personal Papers, Professional Papers, Office Records, Project Records, and Audio-Visual Materials. The bulk of the collection is contained in the Project records series, which includes drawings, photographs, specifications, and other documentation of the projects that Saarinen and his firm designed. Personal papers contain documentation of Saarinen's childhood and personal relationships, as well as his travels. The Professional papers are distinct from the Office records and the Project records in that they contain information about Saarinen's work outside of the process of designing and constructing buildings. This series includes information about Saarinen's awards, his work on committees and juries, and his writings, as well as some documentation of Eliel Saarinen's work. Office records, like the Professional papers, pertain to the work of the architectural firm aside from designing and constructing buildings. Most of the records in this series are public relations and presentation materials. Some financial records of the firm also exist in this series. The small series of Audio-Visual materials primarily contains films about Saarinen's buildings under construction and sound recordings of Saarinen discussing his architecture.
Material concerning one particular project may be found in several series. For example, an award for the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial and Saarinen's writings about the structure will be found in the Professional papers; publicity photographs of the building and scrapbook entries will be found in the Office records; and drawings, correspondence, construction photographs, and specifications for the monument will be found in the Project records.
Similar types of material may be found across series, such as correspondence, photographs, or biographical material. These types of materials are housed in the series that either original order dictated or in the most appropriate series as determined by the archivist. For example, biographical information about Saarinen will be found in the Personal papers, but biographical sketches of Saarinen are also found in Office records, since these sketches were sent out with promotional materials when the firm was attempting to win a commission.
Other collections in the United States containing material related to Saarinen, his family, and his associates include the Saarinen Family Papers at the Cranbrook Archives in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, and the Aline and Eero Saarinen Papers and the Florence Knoll Bassett Papers in the Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
Biographical / Historical
Eero Saarinen was born in Kirkkonummi, Finland on August 20, 1910. His parents, architect Eliel Saarinen and sculptor Loja Gesellius Saarinen, moved to Michigan in 1923 after Eliel Saarinen took second place in the Chicago Tribune tower competition. The Saarinens worked with publisher and philanthropist George C. Booth to create the arts-focused educational community of Cranbrook, in Bloomfield Hills, Michigan. Eero Saarinen attended Cranbrook Academy where his family lived and taught, and, while a student, designed furniture, doors and doorknobs, bricks, and other sculpture for the school and its grounds. After graduating from Cranbrook, Saarinen moved to Paris in 1929 to study sculpture at the Grande Chaumière but returned to the United States to attend architecture school at Yale. He received his Bachelor's degree in Fine Arts in 1934 and briefly worked in the New York office of architect Norman Bel Geddes.
Upon his graduation from Yale, Saarinen was awarded the Charles O. Matcham Travelling Fellowship and traveled throughout Europe, taking photographs, painting watercolor sketches, and making detailed drawings of buildings. When he returned to the United States, he moved back to Michigan to teach alongside his father at Cranbrook and to become a partner, along with his brother-in-law J. Robert F. Swanson, at his firm, renamed Saarinen, Swanson, Saarinen and Associates. Saarinen married sculpture student Lilian Swann in 1939, and the couple became a fixture at Cranbrook, drawing to them a number of designers and artists who would become household names in the decades to come; Charles Eames, Ray Kaiser, Harry Bertoia, Harry Weese, and Ralph Rapson were all friends and collaborators with the Saarinens, and Florence Schust [later Florence Knoll Bassett], a close childhood friend, would commission furniture from both Eames and Saarinen in the coming years. In 1940, Eames' and Saarinen's designs for the Museum of Modern Art's "Organic Furniture" competition won first place and were later exhibited at the museum. In 1942, Eero and Lilian had their first child, Eric, and in 1945 their daughter Susan was born. At this time, Saarinen became a United States citizen, and from 1942 to 1945 he served in the Office of Strategic Services as a designer.
Until Eliel's death in 1950, Eero and his father continued to practice architecture together as Saarinen and Saarinen Associates (Swanson left the firm in 1947), despite Eero's securing his own commissions. Notably, he won the competition for the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial in St. Louis, Missouri -- a competition that his father had also entered and, for a short period, believed he had won. Many of Eero Saarinen's earliest works were collaborations with his father, including the winning entry in the competition for the Smithsonian Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C.; the Des Moines Art Center/Edmundson Memorial Museum; the Crow Island School in Winnetka, Illinois; Tabernacle Church of Christ in Columbus, Indiana; and the early designs for the General Motors Technical Center in Warren, Michigan. After Eliel's death, Eero changed the name of the firm to Eero Saarinen and Associates and emerged as an extremely prolific architect with his own strong creative vision -- one he described as "structural expressionism". He did not hesitate to push the boundaries of what was technologically possible with existing building materials; if a building component didn't exist, he would invent it. His humanistic approach to design and his philosophy of building in "the style for the job" set him apart from his more dogmatically Modernist contemporaries.
In the ten-year period between Eliel's death and Eero's own death, his firm embarked on more than forty projects, including such major works as the Trans World Air Lines Terminal at John F. Kennedy Airport in New York; the John Deere Administrative Center in Moline, Illinois; the Bell Laboratories headquarters in Holmdel, New Jersey; Dulles International Airport in Washington, D.C.; and the Columbia Broadcasting System headquarters in New York. He also continued to work closely with the J. Irwin Miller family of Columbus, Indiana, whose company, the Cummins Engine Company, became one of the great corporate patrons of modern architecture in America. In 1949, A. Whitney Griswold, the president of Yale University, asked Saarinen to create a master plan for the university's anticipated expansion and later awarded him the commissions for Ezra Stiles and Samuel F. B. Morse Colleges and the David S. Ingalls Rink. Between 1948 and 1961 Saarinen served on the Yale University Council as Architecture chairman, as well as its Committees on the Yale Center for Fine Arts and on the Division of the Arts. In 1949 he was awarded an honorary Master of Arts degree from Yale University.
In 1953 Eero and Lilian Saarinen divorced, and that same year Saarinen married Aline Bernstein Louchheim, the arts and architecture editor for the New York Times. Eero and Aline had one son, Eames, in 1954. In 1952, Saarinen was elected a Fellow of the American Institute of Architects and in 1960 became a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Because most of Saarinen's late commissions were on the East Coast of the United States, Saarinen decided, in 1961, to relocate the firm from Bloomfield Hills to Hamden, Connecticut, just a few miles north of the Yale Campus. Tragically, on September 1, 1961, two weeks after being diagnosed with a brain tumor, Saarinen died during surgery, just days before the move was to take place. Ten of his projects remained unfinished and were completed by the surviving members of the reorganized firm known as Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates. The American Institute of Architects posthumously awarded Saarinen its Gold Medal in 1962.
Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architecture -- Indiana -- Columbus; Architecture, Modern -- 20th Century; Architecture, Modern; Design; Furniture design; Patents; Jefferson National Expansion Memorial (Saint Louis, Mo.); Architects; Eames, Charles; Girard, Alexander; Knoll, Florence, 1917-; Miller, J. Irwin (Joseph Irwin), 1909-2004; Saarinen, Aline B. (Aline Bernstein), 1914-1972; Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961; Saarinen, Eliel, 1873-1950; Saarinen, Lilian Swann, 1912-; Antioch College -- Buildings; Athens International Airport; Bell Telephone Laboratories -- Buildings; Berkshire Music Center; CBS Building (New York, N.Y.); Concordia Senior College (Fort Wayne, Ind.) -- Buildings; Deere & Company; Drake University -- Buildings; Dulles International Airport; Ezra Stiles College (Yale University); GM Technical Center; International Business Machines Corporation -- Buildings; Knoll Associates, Inc; Massachusetts Institute of Technology -- Buildings; Morse College (Yale University); Stephens College -- Buildings; Thomas J. Watson IBM Research Center; Trans World Airlines Terminal (New York, N.Y.); United States. Embassy (Great Britain); United States. Embassy (Norway); University of Chicago. Law School; University of Michigan. School of Music; University of Pennsylvania -- Buildings; Vassar College -- Buildings; Vivian Beaumont Theater (Organization: New York, N.Y.); Yale University -- Buildings; Yale University. David S. Ingalls Rink
- Personal Papers, 1920-2004; 1940-1961; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Personal Papers in the Saarinen collection document Saarinen's life outside of his career, including his childhood, student years, and interpersonal relationships. The series consists of the following six subseries: Biographical Information, Correspondence, Diaries and Personal Effects, Photographs, Travel, and Aline Saarinen.
  Personal correspondence includes letters between Saarinen and his family, friends and professional colleagues, his first wife, Lilian Swann Saarinen, and his children, Susan and Eric Saarinen. note that correspondence in this series is listed either by correspondent or topic of correspondence, such as letters written to advocate for the preservation of the Old St. Louis Post Office and the Detroit Old City Hall buildings.
  Diaries and personal effects include Saarinen's annotated desk calendars, memo books, various Finnish and American passports and licenses, personal telephone directories, and "to-do" lists. Of note among these materials is the April, 1957 desk calendar which features an early sketch of the Trans World Flight Center.
  Personal photographs include a large number of family snapshots from Saarinen's early life and school days, as well as posed, professional portraits of Saarinen and other family members. The photographs also document Saarinen's office life, associates, and social life. Included are photographs taken for various magazine articles and other publications. Many, but not all, of the negatives for these photographs are also part of this series.
  The Travel subseries is composed of correspondence and itineraries pertaining to Saarinen's travels as a student to numerous countries and also document later trips taken with family, friends, and professional associates. The photographs and travel slides were taken by Saarinen on these and on earlier trips throughout his childhood and early adulthood, including those taken of buildings and sites on his Charles O. Matcham fellowship trip. While there are documents related to Saarinen's visit to Australia as a juror for the Sydney Opera House competition in this subseries, documentation pertaining to the jury, Saarinen's role on the jury, and its decision does not exist anywhere in this collection.
  The Aline Saarinen subseries consists primarily of biographical information and correspondence about Eero Saarinen. These materials are largely not reflective of her own work and career. Highlights of the correspondence include copies of letters that Aline Saarinen wrote to Cranston Jones of Time magazine in 1956 about her husband's personality quirks and working style. Time would later publish a cover story on the architect and his family. The correspondence includes a large number of letters of condolence that she received after Eero Saarinen's death. The series encompasses correspondence, page proofs, and drafts for her book, published after Eero's death, entitled Eero Saarinen on His Work. Photographs of Aline Saarinen are in the Photographs subseries.
  - Saarinen, Eero
    - Biographical information
      - Biographical outline, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Clippings [obituaries,editorials, and reactions to death], 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
      - Divorce from Lilian Swann Saarinen, 1953-1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Financial ledger, 1947-1953 (Box 2)
      - Financial records, 1950-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Legal papers, 1949-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Lists of contributors to Saarinen memorial fund at Yale University, Circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Press release from Eero Saarinen & Associates upon Saarinen's death, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Real estate
        - 288 Townshend property, Birmingham, Michigan, 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Vaughan Road residence, Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, 1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - 1658 Webster mortgage correspondence, Birmingham, Michigan, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Hvitträsk property, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 13)
        - Valley Road property, North Branford, Connecticut, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - 10 St. Ronan Terrace residence, New Haven, Connecticut, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Student work
        - The Broadcaster, student newspaper from Station Union High School, Ann Arbor, Michigan, 1925-1926 (Box 677, Folder 97)
          General
          See: Oversize Folder 97
        - "A Police Station" [first-place student project at Yale], Circa 1931-1934 (Folder 4)
          General note
          See also: Series I. Personal Papers, 1920-2004 (inclusive), 1940-1961 (bulk) Folder 79
      - Text of memorial service and lists of invitees, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Transcript of CBS News program: "Accent: Eero Saarinen: An Appreciation", 1961 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence
      - Blake, Peter, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Bolton, Frances, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Brody, Peter, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - de Rivoire, Kirre, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Detroit Old City Hall, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Family members, miscellaneous, 1956, 1958, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Floor lamp designed by Eliel Saarinen, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Kennedy Inauguration, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Library of Congress solicitation, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Lundquist, Oliver [reminiscences of Eero Saarinen with annotations from Robert A. M. Stern], 2004 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Miller, J. Irwin, 1949, 1958, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Milles, Carl, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Personal residence [draperies, rug, tabletops], 1956 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Saarinen, Eric and Susan, 1954-1961 (Box 3, Folder 31 - 34)
      - Saarinen, Lilian Swann, 1947-1961 (Box 5, Folder 35 - 36)
      - Sampe, Astrid, 1953, 1956, 1958, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 37)
      - St. Louis, Old Post Office, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 38)
      - Weese, Harry, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 39)
      - Wright, Frank Lloyd: gift set of photostats of drawings for Guggenheim Museum, undated (Box 677, Folder 98)
      - Yale School of Architecture Beaux-Arts Ball, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 40)
      - Miscellaneous, 1929, 1934, 1944, 1949, 1953, 1957-1961 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Diaries and personal effects
      - Desk calendars, monthly, 1951 July-1961 September (Box 696, Folder 195)
      - Memo book, passports, driving licenses, membership cards, printed memorabilia, wallet, 1929-1964, undated (Box 5, Folder 42)
      - Personal telephone directories, undated (Box 6, Box 5, Folder 43 - 45)
      - "To-Do" lists, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
    - Photographs
      - Childhood and family photographs
        - 1920s-1930s album, negatives and contact sheets, Circa 1920-1930 (Box 6, Folder 47)
        - Childhood home, undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
        - Childhood in Finland [includes negatives], undated (Box 6, Folder 49 - 50)
        - Early adulthood, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
        - Family photographs and contact sheets, Circa 1950-1960 (Box 6, Folder 52 - 53)
        - Knoll, Florence (Shust), undated (Box 7, Folder 54)
        - Saarinen, Aline (Bernstein), undated (Box 7, Folder 55 - 56)
        - Saarinen, Eliel and Loja [includes negatives], undated (Box 7, Folder 57 - 58)
        - Saarinen, Eliel with Eero, undated (Box 7, Folder 59)
        - Saarinen family caricatures, undated (Box 7, Folder 60)